Chirag Gupta, Ph.D.

Scientist I
Waisman Center, University of Wisconsin
Madison, Wisconsin, USA

Webpage: cngupta.github.io Email: cngupta@protonmail.com





SUMMARY

Computational biologist with 5+ years of postdoctoral experience in research and analysis of multi-modal genomics data. Specifically, my research straddles between **regulatory genomics**, **network biology**, and **machine learning** with an aim to develop computationally tractable models of human diseases. I am currently working on projects focused on strategies to guide disease **biomarker discovery**, **drug repurposing**, and **patient stratification** using **multi-modal single-cell** genomic data of the **human brain**. I have extensive experience in written and oral communication to academics and business leaders through contributions to winning grants, 12+ peer reviewed publications, and several conference appearances.

EDUCATION

2017	Ph.D. Computational Biology	
	(Cell and Molecular Biology)	University of Arkansas,
	Dissertation: Transcriptome-based gene networks for systems-level analysis of gene function	Fayetteville, Arkansas, USA
2000	, ,	
2009	M.Sc. Bioinformatics	
2007	B.Sc. Bioinformatics	Sardar Patel University, India

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

2023 – present	Scientist I • PsychENCODE2, PsychAD	
	Single cell network biologyNeuropsychiatric disorders	University of Wisconsin,
2021 – 2023	 Postdoctoral Research Associate Single-cell gene regulatory networks 	Madison, Wisconsin, USA
	Network medicineAlzheimer's disease	
2017 – 2020	Postdoctoral Research Associate	
	 Plant and crop genomics Machine learning for gene prioritization 	University of Arkansas,
2012 – 2017	Web-applications Graduate Research Assistant	Fayetteville, Arkansas, USA
	Plant stress and developmental biologyLarge-scale transcriptomics	
2008 — 2009	 Gene regulatory networks Student Researcher 	Disha Life Sciences Pvt. Ltd.,
	Hallmarks of fusion proteins in cancerMolecular modeling, drug designing	Gujarat, India

PUBLICATIONS

Under review/preprints

- 1. Yheni Dwiningsih, Julie Thomas, Anuj Kumar, **Chirag Gupta**, Navdeep Gill, Charles Ruiz, Jawaher Alkahtani, Niranjan Baisakh, Andy Pereira. Identification of QTLs and Candidate Loci Associated with Drought-Related Traits of the K/Z RIL Rice Population. (*preprint*)
- 2. **Chirag Gupta**, Arjun Krishnan, Andrew Schneider, Cynthia Denbow, Eva Collakova, Pawel Wolinski, Andy Pereira. SANe: The Seed Active Network for Discovering Transcriptional Regulatory Programs of Seed Development. (*preprint*)

Peer reviewed journal articles

- 1. **Chirag Gupta**, Jielin Xu, Ting Jin, Saniya Khullar, Xiaoyu Liu, Sayali Alatkar, Feixiong Cheng, Daifeng Wang. Single-cell network biology characterizes cell type gene regulation for drug repurposing and phenotype prediction in Alzheimer's disease. **PLOS Computational Biology**, July 2022. [full text] [cover story]
- Chirag Gupta, Pramod Chandrashekar, Chenfeng He, Ting Jin, Saniya Khullar, Qiang Chang, Daifeng Wang. Bringing machine learning to research on intellectual and developmental disabilities: taking inspiration from neurological diseases. *Journal of Neurodevelopmental Disorders* (IDDRC 2022 special issue on computational neuroscience), *May 2022*. [full text]
- 3. Anuj Kumar, **Chirag Gupta**, Julie Thomas, Andy Pereira. Genetic Dissection of Grain Yield Component Traits Under High Nighttime Temperature Stress in a Rice Diversity Panel. **Frontiers in Plant Science**, September 2021. [full text]
- 4. **Chirag Gupta**, Venkategowda Ramegowda, Supratim Basu, Andy Pereira. Using network-based machine learning to predict transcription factors involved in drought stress resistance. *Frontiers in Genetics*, *June 2021*. [full text]
- 5. Raksha Singh, Rohana Liyanage, **Chirag Gupta**, Jackson Lay Jr., Andy Pereira, Clemencia Rojas. The protein interactomes of AtNHR2A and AtNHR2B unraveled common and specialized functions in plant immunity integrating distinct biological processes. *Frontiers in Plant Science*, *March 2020. [full text]*
- 6. Min Woo Lee, Carmen S. Padilla, **Chirag Gupta**, Aravind Galla, Andy Pereira, Jiamei Li, Fiona L. Goggin. The FATTY ACID DESATURASE 2 family in tomato contributes to primary metabolism and stress responses. *Plant Physiology*, *Nov. 2019.* [full text]
- 7. **Chirag Gupta** and Andy Pereira. Recent advances in gene function prediction using context-specific coexpression networks in plants. *F1000Research*, Feb. 2019. [full text]
- 8. Arjun Krishnan, **Chirag Gupta**, Madana MR Ambavaram, Andy Pereira. RECoN: Rice Environment Co-expression Network for systems level analysis of abiotic-stress response. *Frontiers in Plant Science*, Sep. 2017. [full text]

- 9. Venkategowda Ramegowda, Upinder Singh Gill, Palaiyur Nanjappan Sivalingam, Aarti Gupta, **Chirag Gupta**, Geetha Govind, Karaba N Nataraja, Andy Pereira, Makarla Udayakumar, Kirankumar S Mysore, Muthappa Senthil-Kumar. GBF3 transcription factor imparts drought tolerance in Arabidopsis thaliana. *Scientific Reports*, *August 2017.* [full text]
- 10. Venkategowda Ramegowda, Supratim Basu, **Chirag Gupta**, Andy Pereira. Regulation of grain yield in rice under well-watered and drought stress conditions by GUDK. *Plant Signaling and Behavior*, *January 2015.* [full text]

CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS

Select talks

- Single-cell network biology characterizes cell type gene regulation for drug repurposing and phenotype prediction in Alzheimer's disease. Alzheimer's Association International Conference, San Diego, CA, 2nd August 2022
- Predicting rice genes important for drought tolerance using gene regulatory networks and machine learning. Crops InSilico, 4th Annual Symposium and Hackathon, Urbana, IL, 3rd May 2019
- Arabidopsis seed-filling association-network analysis. American Society of Plant Biologists – Southern Section (ASPB-SS), Lexington, KY, 30th March 2014.

Select posters

- Single-cell network biology characterizes cell type gene regulation for drug repurposing and phenotype prediction in Alzheimer's disease, Intelligent Systems for Molecular Biology, Madison, WI, July 2022
- Network analysis of human brain cell types under Alzheimer's disease and healthy conditions, Society of Neuroscience, Chicago, IL, November 2021
- Network-based approach to prioritize lung cancer genes from whole-exome sequencing data. Arkansas Bioinformatics Consortium, Little Rock, AR, 25th March 2018
- [Award winning poster] An abiotic-stress conditioned gene regulatory network in rice predicted using an ensemble of reverse-engineering solutions. The 25th Plant and Animal Genome (PAG) Conference, San Diego, CA, 14th January 2017
- A resource for systems analysis of stress response in rice. NSF Workshop on plant development and drought stress, Monterey, CA, 8th November 2015
- In Silico Analysis of Fusion Proteins in Cancer, International Conference on Biomedical and Genomic Research, Ahmedabad, India, 30th January 2009

AWARDS

- 1. Crops in silico underrepresented minority travel scholarship, **Crops InSilico**, Urbana, IL, 2019
- 2. Scherago International Student Travel Grants Awards, **The 25th annual Plant and Animal Genome (PAG) meeting**, San Diego, CA, 2017
- 3. NSF Travel Grant to attend the Workshop on Plant Development and Drought Stress, **National Science Foundation**, 2015
- 4. Stood 3rd in merit list for all India entrance examination for Master's in bioinformatics program, **Sardar Patel University**, India, 2007
- 5. 2nd Prize in undergraduate oral presentation, Sardar Patel University, India, 2006
- 6. 3rd Prize in undergraduate poster competition, Atmiya University, India, 2006

GRANT CONTRIBUTIONS

- NSF EPSCoR RII Track-2 FEC 1826836: Systems genetics studies on rice genomes for analysis of grain yield and quality under heat stress (PI: Dr. Andy Pereira; \$4,659,406), 2018
- **NSF MCB 1716844**: Systems genetics analysis of photosynthetic carbon metabolism in rice (PI: Dr. Andy Pereira; \$798,725.00), 2017

SOCIETY MEMBERSHIPS

2019 - present
2022 - present
The International Society for Computational Biology (ISCB)
The Alzheimer's Association International Society to Advance

Alzheimer's Research and Treatment (ISTAART)

SELECT SKILLS

Programming R, Python, Perl

Bioinformatics Expertise with standard sequence data (NGS) processing pipelines (single-

cell, bulk mRNA, ATAC-seq, ChiP) including quality control, alignment, variant

calling, differential expression, and integration

Data science Extensive experience with data science and machine learning tools in R

(caret, e1071, tidyr, dplyr, ggplot2) and Python (NumPy, SciPy, Scikit, Dask,

Keras)

Computing Fluency with developing automated bioinformatics workflows using Docker,

Platforms Shiny; Google Cloud

TOOLS DEVELOPED

GRAiN http://rrn.uark.edu/shiny/apps/GRAiN/
SANe https://plantstress-pereira.uark.edu/SANe/
RECoN https://plantstress-pereira.uark.edu/RECoN/

MENTORING EXEPRIENCE

Mentored a graduate student (Masters in Statistics, UW) and four undergraduate students under the University of Madison's Undergraduate Research Scholar contract for two semesters, 2021-2022. Project title: "Using network-based machine Learning to predict genes underlying neurological disorders"

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Co-taught Plant Genomics (**Bioinformatics/Genomics modules**: CSES 5543, Uni. Of Arkansas), 2016, 2018

EXTENSION ACTIVITIES

Student and Teacher Workshop: rice genetic variation (18 credit hours, Uni. Of Arkansas), 2019

ACADEMIC SERVICE

- Youth Editor for iMeta, Wiley Online Library, Sep. 2022
- External reviewer for IEEE International Conference on Bioinformatics and Biomedicine (BIBM) 2022.
- Specialty review editor for Frontiers in Bioinformatics and Frontiers in Genetics
- **Manuscript reviewer** for Human Molecular Genetics, Journal of Neurodevelopmental Disorders, Plant Physiology, Frontiers in Plant Science, Nature Scientific Reports, Rice, Plant Cell Reports, Horticultural Plant Journal, Plant Methods, PLoS One, iMETA.
- **Plante Fellow 2019**: Contribution to the Plantae online portal for Bioinformatics resources relevant to plant biology research
- Member of the panel of judges for the Northwest Arkansas Regional Science and Engineering Fair 2015,16
- Conducted several training material and hands-on activities for undergraduates and K-12 students from the Arkansas agricultural areas in the Delta region for a STEM literacy outreach program

REFREES

Available upon request